All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Good מוצאי שבועות. Motzei Shavuot. We are on today's דף י"ד. Daf
Yud Dalet. We pick up י"ג עמוד ב Yud Gimmel Amud Bet
about twelve lines down, נכסים המיוחדים. Nechasim Hamiyuchadim. We're going through the
משנה Mishnah and discussing what are some of the parameters, broad parameters
that you're חייב chayav for נזק, nezek, and one of the things
the משנה Mishnah mentions is designated property or assigned property, so we're
going to have to see what this phrase means. Okay,
so למעוטי מאי? Lemautei Mai? What does that exclude? By the two
dots, about twelve lines down, י"ג עמוד ב, Yud Gimmel Amud Bet,
אמר רב יהודה למעוטי זה אומר שורך הזיק וזה אומר שורך הזיק.
Amar Rav Yehuda Lemautei Zeh Omer Shorcha Hezik Vezeh Omer Shorcha Hezik.
So it's not clear whose ox did the damage. Two oxen were
running after my ox, and my ox got gored and each property,
and ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are both pointing the finger at
one another. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הא תני לקמן, Ha
Tani Lakamman, what, you don't need this משנה Mishnah to tell us
that? That's a משנה Mishnah later. היו שנים רודפים אחר אחד, Hayu
Shenayim Rodfim Achar Echad, two oxen were running after one ox, זה
אומר שורך הזיק וזה אומר שורך הזיק, Zeh Omer Shorcha Hezik Vezeh
Omer Shorcha Hezik, ראובן Reuven says שמעון Shimon's ox did it, שמעון
Shimon says ראובן Reuven's ox did it, שנים פטורים, Shenayim Peturin, they're
both exempt. It's your classic המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav
Haraya.
All right, תני ואדר מפרש, Tani Ve'ader Mefaresh, first it gave a
very like an abstract statement and then it made it clear what
it was talking about, especially because this whole משנה Mishnah is so
cryptic to begin with. All right, that's one read of the משנה.
Mishnah. ובמתניתא תנא, Uvematnita Tana, the ברייתא Braita we taught, פרט לנכסי
הפקר, Prat Lenichsei Hefker, that it means owned property as opposed to
ownerless property. Okay, היכי דמי? Heichi Dami? What's the case? So what
are we talking about? The damaging or the damaged ox is ownerless.
אילימא דנגח תורא דידן לתורא דהפקר, Ileima Denagach Tora Didan Letora Dehefker,
if one of our oxen gored a הפקר Hefker ox, מאן תבע
ליה? Man Tavei Lei? So of course you're exempt. Who's going to
bring you to בית דין? Beis Din? אלא, Ella, I mean if
you could take possession of the animal, obviously if you damage it
you can't be sued. אלא דנגח תורא דהפקר לתורא דידן, Ella Denagach
Tora Dehefker Letora Didan,
an ownerless ox gored one of ours, so ליזיל וליתי, Leizei Veleisei,
so what's the חידוש Chiddush there? Just go ahead and take possession
of the ox. It's ownerless anyway. You want to get your money
back? Go ahead, take possession of the ox. It's ownerless. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, בשקדם וזכה בו אחר, Beshekadam Vezacha Bo Acher,
let's say there was an ownerless ox, it gored my ox, and
then ראובן Reuven took possession of it. Now you would say still,
like which owner are you going to hold liable? Nobody owned it
when it gored my ox. Ah, but what we have to remember
is that the הלכה Halacha is when an ox gores an ox,
for the first three times you pay half, but what's the other
הלכה Halacha in addition to paying half? Where does the money come
out of? Anybody remember? The body of the ox itself, okay? So
therefore it's a simple case. An ownerless ox gored mine, maybe it's
a reasonable thing to think the הלכה Halacha would be even though
there's no owner for me to sue for negligence, maybe I automatically
become owner of the ox, of, you know, if there were a
hundred dollars of damage in my ox I become an owner of
a hundred dollars of this הפקר Hefker ox. You say what difference
does it make? I could just take full possession. No, I can't
take full possession because before I found the ox, מיכאל Michael here
took possession of it. So maybe I should say okay, but I
already own a hundred dollars from the moment it did damage to
me. And the חידוש Chiddush is that that's not true. Without an
owner, I don't own any part of an ox that damaged mine
if that ox had no owner. Okay, now that could just be
an arbitrary exemption, or no, the more logical thing to be to
say would be that the whole נזיקין Nezikin starts with the sense
that there's a person who is liable, either liable for their negligence
or liable because their property did damage, but it does not start
by some metaphysical reality that if oxes damage my ox, I become,
the ox is to blame and I own a part of the
ox. So without an owner, nothing gets started. Okay, so that's the
חידוש. Chiddush. If an ownerless ox gored mine, I do not become
an owner, a part owner in that ox. All right, that's a
nice חידוש. Chiddush. I mean it's logical, but it's an important point
to be made. Okay, רבינא אמר, Ravina Amar, that's explanation number two
what נכסים המיוחדים Nechasim Hamiyuchadim mean. רבינא אמר למעוטי נגח ואחר כך
הקדיש נגח ואחר כך הפקיר, Ravina Amar Lemautei Nagach Ve'achar Kach Hikdish
Nagach Ve'achar Kach Hefkir, even a bigger חידוש. Chiddush. My ox gored
and after it gored and I'm liable, I sanctify it, I give
it to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, or after it gored I
renounce ownership, and therefore I'm not going to have to pay. Now
that's a pretty bizarre idea that I can get out of paying.
Let's take a look. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya Nami Hachi, we taught
similarly, יותר הן אמרו Yoser hen amru רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda said more than whatever he said before, אף אילו
נגח ואחר כך הקדיש נגח ואחר כך הפקיר פטור, Af Illu Nagach
Ve'achar Kach Hikdish Nagach Ve'achar Kach Hefkir Patur, if
you after gored you sanctify it or renounce ownership you're exempt. Now
this specific פסוק Pasuk we're going to be dealing with is a
case of כופר, Kofer, of
paying the atonement payment if it kills a person. I think that's
explicitly, that's going to be the פסוק, Pasuk, I think it's also
explicitly the case of,
yeah, that's specifically the case over there later as well, is the
case about paying the כופר Kofer payment. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
says if you מפקיר Mafkir or מקדיש Maqdish it, you don't pay
the כופר Kofer payment, שנאמר והועד בבעליו, shene'emar Vehuad Beva'alav, you were...
Warned against the owner and he killed a man or a woman
who will be stoned and also its owner will be put to
death. Anyway, so the דרשה derasha is עד שתהא מיתה והעמדה בדין
שוין. ad she-tehei misa ve-ha-amada ba-din shavin.
It's והועד בבעליו והמית איש, ve-hu-ad bi-ve-alav ve-hameis ish, so it killed
somebody and then where's the העמדה בדין ha-amada ba-din in the פסוק?
pasuk? So it's השור יסקל ha-shor yisakail where the דרשה derasha is
really at the end of the פסוק. pasuk. והמית איש והשור יסקל.
ve-hameis ish ve-ha-shor yisakail.
So the killing, the goring it did, and then the fact that
it was judged to be liable the death penalty is all in
the same context. It's not that it became it transferred ownership in
the middle. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, גמר דין לא
בעינן? gmar din lo bainan? What do you mean? Why did you
say standing in judgment has to be in the same context?
Presumably, it's the it's the sealing of the judgment, the issuing of
the judgment. השור יסקל, ha-shor yisakail, בגמר דין הוא דכתיב. be-gmar din
hu de-chsiv. The דרשה derasha is on the end of the פסוק:
pasuk: השור יסקל, ha-shor yisakail, and that's when it's judged to be
liable. אלא אימא ela eima עד שתהא מיתה, ad she-tehei misa, so
it's והמית איש או אשה השור יסקל. ve-hameis ish o isha ha-shor
yisakail. So from the moment it kills till the moment it's judged
to be a שור הנסקל, shor ha-niskal, that has to be בגמר
דין שוין כאחד be-gmar din shavin ke-echad in the same context. Now
there's a couple of questions here. What does that mean it has
to be the same context? Let's say my ox gores somebody and
he dies, and then I transfer ownership to Michael. That's not שוין
כאחד. shavin ke-echad. It's not, right? Or transfer ownership to my wife,
even better. Okay, that's not owned by the same person. Is that
enough? So it seems like no. Only if it's הפקר hefker or
הקדש, hekdesh, because הפקר hefker and הקדש hekdesh is a type of
an ownership that would be exempt had the ox gored when it
was a הקדש hekdesh ox. Had the ox gored when it was
a הפקר hefker ox, it would have been exempt. So if I
transferred it into an exempt status before העמדה בדין, ha-amada ba-din, I'm
off the hook. Okay. Now let's say the רשויות מאי, reshuyos mai,
I transfer to the exempt status and then I reclaim it. I
מפקיר mafkir it and I reclaim it. Do I also get off
or is it only when it's in that exempt status at the
moment of העמדה בדין? ha-amada ba-din? Okay, so that's like an open
question. Now that's the case by כופר. kofer. The funny thing is
the גמרא, Gemara, one minute, the גמרא Gemara without any basis in
a פסוק, pasuk, without without connecting the dots, did not tell me
how I go from the כופר kofer idea to say I'm exempt
to a case of a normal ox that gores another ox. And
there's a big difference, right? כופר kofer is an atonement payment. Somebody
died. It's not actual compensation. You might think that that really requires
much more of a formal process imposed by the court. When my
ox just damages property, right, why should why should there be this
rule that I get off if I'm מפקיר mafkir before העמדה בדין?
ha-amada ba-din? Even more than that, think about the irony in it.
My ox gores a thousand dollars worth of property. It's a hundred
dollar ox. I have a great out. I just מפקיר mafkir the
ox. Now I don't have to pay for the thousand dollars of
damage that it did. So it's very very strange. The גמרא Gemara
doesn't explain how it learns to apply this כופר kofer to other
things, and there's a profound injustice. Now it's possible and some אחרונים
acharonim speculate, maybe the גמרא Gemara only means it by קרן תם.
keren tam. A קרן תם, keren tam, right, a
an unhabituated ox that gores, there's two reasons why this הלכה halacha
would make sense by that. Number one is that that might be
a קנס knas and not ממון. mamon. That's going to be a
debate later on. But when my ox gores the first three times
and I'm not expecting it and I only pay half, that might
be seen as something I shouldn't have expected, I really should get
off the hook, it's only seen as like a fine, not real
compensation. If that's true, you need the בית דין beis din to
impose the fine. It's not like the liability happens automatically, right?
Normally, if if if my ox gores yours and it's done it
three times or tramples, eats your food, or your ox falls into
my well, I'm automatically liable. בית דין beis din just clarifies, you
know, you know, the reality, but automatically I owe you money as
soon as the events occur. That's in a normal case of compensation.
If I damaged you, that that that debt obligation exists automatically, בית
דין beis din just clarifies that that actually is what happened. Whereas
if it's a fine, the debt doesn't happen automatically. בית דין beis
din imposes the fine. So there you could understand that if the
קנס, knas, if the paying the half damages is a type of
a קנס, knas, without בית דין's beis din involvement, I don't owe
anything. And since by the time בית דין beis din gets involved,
the ox is by this stage it's ownerless or it's הקדש, hekdesh,
בית דין beis din cannot impose that fine because it's in a
different status. So number one, if we're talking about half damages, it
makes sense why this type you know technically why this exemption could
work because you need בית דין beis din to impose the fine
and by the time בית דין beis din gets involved the ox
is in a different status. Not only does it make sense technically,
it deals with the injustice problem. Why does it deal with the
injustice problem? 'Cause when my ox the first three times gores, what
is the limit of my liability?
Half. Half of the damages and what else is it limited by?
The value of the ox. So I don't get save myself any
money by being מפקיר mafkir the ox, right? When my ox gores,
for the first three times, I never have to pay more than
the value of the ox.
of the ox. I could be losing money by מפקיר. mafkir.
I could be losing money. So it deals with the injustice problem,
alright? So it's very strange that the גמרא Gemara applies this idea
that applies by כופר kofer to normal types of payment. And, A,
it's unjust, unjust, and B, it doesn't make sense technically. And it
works very well, although the גמרא Gemara isn't clear about this, if
we limit it to the payment of a תם. tam. Therefore you
understand why technically you need it to be in the same status
because you need the בית דין Beis Din to impose the קנס
knas and you don't owe the money until בית דין Beis Din
imposes the קנס. knas. And number two, it solves the injustice problem
because anyway my liability is limited to the value of my ox.
Yes.
So if it's really a קנס, knas, then first of all, you
can't do תפיסה, tefisa, right? Because אין דנין דיני קנסות בבבל. Ein
danin dinei knasot be-Bavel.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that. Yeah.
Okay. Alright. Alright, now, so that's...
Wait, wouldn't you think like sort of like almost let's say מקדיש
נכסי השם, makdish nichsei Hashem, like you know if I'm מפקיר mafkir
this ox,
like you
know...
You don't mean מפקיר, mafkir, you mean מקדיש. makdish. I mean מקדיש.
makdish. Okay.
Alright, fine, I hear the point. Alright, חוץ מרשות המיוחדת למזיק. Chutz
me-reshut ha-meyuchedet la-mazik.
Now, that's the case of נכסים מיוחדים, nechasim meyuchedim, which is this
interesting הלכה halacha about being מפקיר mafkir your ox after it did
the damage. Now, the exemption, תוספות Tosafot says you're exempt for paying
is when it's in... when the damage occurs in the מזיק's mazik
property. דאמר ליה, De-amar lei, because your ox wanders into my property
and my ox gores it, or you left your fruit in my
property and my ox eats it. So I say to you, תורך
ברשותי מאי בעי? Torecha bi-reshuti mai ba'ei? What's your ox doing in
my property? You know, buddy, you walked in here on your own
accord, nobody gave you permission, so I'm exempt from any damage that
occurs here. You don't have a right to be here. I have
a right to do whatever I want in my property. You know,
I mean it's a problem nowadays of course with what do you
call it, you know, with people that shoot people that walk on
their property. You know, I'm serious, it's like you know, the sense
of protecting your homestead, right? So you can do whatever you want
if somebody wanders into your property. But here at least we're not
talking about willful damage, alright? We're talking about, you know, your property
damages and you have a right, you don't have to watch your
own animal in your own property. You can let them do whatever
the heck you want, and if you walk in, you're taking that
risk upon yourself. I have no liability for what happens to you
or to your animals or to your fruit if you walk into
my property. Now, what you would want to say, although the גמרא
Gemara is not explicit, but the ראשונים Rishonim say it explicitly, is
this only means if you walk in without permission. Right? If I
give you permission, what do you mean what am I doing on
your property? You let me, you invited me into your property. Okay,
so that could be very different and that could be a case
where I do have rights and we'll get to that in a
minute. But it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara did not spell
that out explicitly. And actually, you know, in I think civil law,
in secular law, if I give you permission to come onto my
property, I have heightened liability, right? Because it's... that's why people get
like homeowner's insurance, you know, for accidents that occur on their property.
So anyway, but if you don't have rights to be on it,
it's not my problem, it's not my fault, and I am completely
exempt from any damages. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, so that's an important idea that we will see come up
elsewhere, but here the גמרא Gemara just says it in like one
sentence. Yes.
If somebody's being a little... What about the שור המועד? shor ha-mu'ad?
I don't want to go back to that.
Doesn't one remove a נזק? nezek?
Yes, we will get to that as well. ורשות הניזק והמזיק. Ve-reshut
ha-nizak ve-ha-mazik. Okay,
now, here is a complicated line in the משנה. Mishnah. So the
משנה Mishnah says like this, the משנה Mishnah says, right, just to
read the line in the משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah
says... I gotta go back to the משנה. Mishnah. Okay.
It says the things you're liable for, right? It says,
חבתי בתשלומי נזקו, Chavti be-tashlumei nizko, חבתי בתשלומי נזקו, Chavti be-tashlumei nizko,
the משנה Mishnah said, you know, if you're things you're liable for,
etc. And then it lists the things you're חייב chayav for. שאין
בהן מעילה, She-ein bahen me'ilah, okay, which is what we dealt with
yesterday, things that aren't הקדש, hekdesh, בני ברית, bnei bris, they're owned
by Jews,
מיוחדים, meyuchadim, which is we dealt with the case about הפקר. hefker.
Okay, and ובכל מקום חוץ, u-vekhol makom chutz, okay, חוץ מרשות המיוחדת
למזיק. chutz me-reshut ha-meyuchedet la-mazik. Okay, now, המיוחדת, ha-meyuchedet, one minute, למזיק.
la-mazik. So you're not liable if it happens in your domain. Alright.
ורשות הניזק והמזיק. Ve-reshut ha-nizak ve-ha-mazik. Now, here's the... so here's the
tough line.
ורשות הניזק והמזיק, Ve-reshut ha-nizak ve-ha-mazik, let's say it's a shared domain
between the damager and the damagee. ורשות הניזק והמזיק, Ve-reshut ha-nizak ve-ha-mazik,
and then it says, כשהזיק חב המזיק לשלם.
ke-she-hizik chav
ha-mazik le-shalem. כשהזיק חב המזיק לשלם. Ke-she-hizik chav ha-mazik le-shalem.
So the question is, where does this line go?
Is you're exempt when it's in your domain and when it's in
a shared domain? And now going back to the general principle, you're
liable to pay in all these cases with this exception, and when
it damages... you're liable to pay. So the question is this last
line, is this part of the exemption, right? This is the חוץ
chutz line, okay? Is that the חוץ chutz and and then we
go back to say oh by the way the general point is
you're liable to pay. So when it's in a shared domain you're
exempt, or are we saying no you're exempt when it happens in
your domain, but when it's in a shared domain then you also
then you do have to pay? Alright so two very very ambiguous
line in the משנה. Mishna. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara.
Okay. רשות הניזק והמזיק. Reshut hanizak vehamazik. אמר רב חסדא אמר אבימי.
Amar Rav Chisda amar Avimi. חצר השותפין Chatzar hashtufin if it is
a shared
domain חייב על השן ועל הרגל. chayav al hashen veal haregel. You're
חייב chayav on שן shen and רגל. regel. Now in the גמרא,
Gemara, the question of a shared domain is only going to be
a question of שן shen and רגל, regel, not of קרן. keren.
Why? Because קרן keren you're חייב chayav in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
קרן keren you're חייב chayav everywhere. The only place you're exempt for
קרן keren is if it's in my domain and you brought your
cow without permission into my domain. So if it's a shared domain
should I be חייב chayav in קרן? keren? What do you think?
You just said yes.
Yes, the only time I would be exempt is if it's only
my domain and you have no right to be here. That's the
only time I get off for קרן. keren. So any if it's
a shared domain and you have a right to be here, of
course I'm חייב chayav in קרן. keren. So a shared domain there's
no question you're חייב chayav in קרן. keren. The more interesting question
is what is the story of a case of שן shen and
רגל? regel? Okay so what is the הלכה halacha of שן shen
and רגל? regel? Where are you חייב chayav in שן shen and
רגל? regel?
What does the Torah say? What's the פסוק? pasuk? Where do we
know? Let me start the other... וביער
בשדה אחר. uve'er besadeh acher. You're חייב chayav by שן shen and
רגל regel when it does it in the other person's property. Where
are you exempt? What's the general הלכה? halacha? שן shen and רגל
regel is exempt in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Excellent. So here is
the case of the problem of the excluded middle, when you describe
the two extremes and you don't deal with the middle case. Okay
one extreme is I'm חייב chayav when it's in the other person's
property. I'm exempt when it's in the public domain. Okay there's a
lot of stuff that's between the other person's property and the public
domain. And let's say there's a shared domain. Okay now you could
say I am liable, the only time I get off is when
it's a public domain and like there's tons of animals roaming around,
everybody has to be aware, you leave your food down you're doing
it at your own risk, you know, I have a right to
have my animals in the public domain, the law can't constrict me
by making me pay. So there's special exemption in the public domain.
Anything that's not the main thoroughfare on the public domain I'm going
to be liable. That's one way of looking at it, right? So
then a shared domain of just me and one other person I
would be liable. I don't have that broad exemption of a public
domain. The other way of thinking is no,
fundamentally the only case you're חייב chayav is when it made incursion
into a space you had no right to be there. If this
is a space that we both have a right to be there,
then it's not שדה אחר sadeh acher and I'm exempt. Okay so
right you understand right how do you look at it? Do you
say right רשות הרבים reshut harabim is that that's when you're exempt
because why? Because I mean it's important to remind us logic of
why you should be exempt by רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. There's a
couple of reasons. Number one is you have to just give me
freedom
of use of
the public thoroughfare, okay? And also
because of פשיעת הניזק. pshiat hanizak. You know because you're stupid enough
to put your stuff down in a place where everybody's animals is
going around or whatever you know you did it to yourself. So
that's a special reason to be exempt in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim.
Okay so anything that wouldn't be that you'd be חייב. chayav. At
the other end of the spectrum we have שדה אחר. sadeh acher.
And there there's a special reason to be חייב chayav because my
animal you know did an incursion
into some property that it was not that it didn't have a
right to.
And it did it in that property what it does in...
into someone else's property, so therefore I'm specifically חייב chayav because my
animal had no right to be there. Alright but what about all
this space in between? Okay if it's חצר השותפין, chatzar hashtufin, okay
on the one hand it has a right to be there.
So if we say specifically because it incursion into another property it
should be exempt. On the other hand it doesn't have all the
special reasons to be exempt of רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, right? So
it depends on which way do you look at it. Do you
look at it fundamentally you shouldn't pay except if it's שדה אחר?
sadeh acher? Only if there's a special reason to pay do you
pay, and then here you'd be exempt. Or do you look at
it as fundamentally you should be חייב chayav unless you have a
very special reason to be exempt, right? So you see how which
are we focusing on? Are we focusing on that you're exempt in
רשות הרבים? reshut harabim? Then you should be חייב chayav on anything
that's not a רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Or are we looking at
it as you're חייב chayav in שדה אחר? sadeh acher? When it's
in
the other
property...
Yeah, I get it, it's like the case of excluded middle, you
keep on saying there's like a whole lot of stuff in between
the extremes. What else is there besides חצר השותפין? hatzar hashutfinn?
Well, how about a third person's domain or how about a... how
about, I don't know, how about the sides, the edges of רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, the צידי רשות הרבים tzidei reshut harabbim where I
sort of have a right to be but it's not as much
of a public thoroughfare, it's not as widely traveled? We can imagine
a lot of other cases, and even if there is only one,
the point is that you're still... are you explaining only by שדה
אחר sedeh acher you're חייב hayyav or only by רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim you're פטור? patur? Okay, yes.
Yeah, and it takes into consideration of... when you're sharing a space
that each person should be responsible for each other one separate from
this question of the quality of the space itself.
Right, but that's also something you could say about רשות הרבים. reshut
harabbim. It's also where we're all sharing a space, it's just there's
so many of us sharing the space it might lead to special
consideration. But you're right. I mean you could get into the specific
logic about what's the logic here. But I just want to also
just consider you know sort of you know appreciate that it's situated
between those two. So that's going to be the debate. Okay, so
let's take a look.
אמר רב חסדא אמר אבימי: Amar Rav Hisda amar Avimi: חצר השותפין
חייב בה על השן ועל הרגל. Hatzar hashutfinn hayyav bah al hashen
ve'al haregel. You're חייב. hayyav. והכי קאמר: Vehachi ka'amar: חוץ מרשות המיוחדת
למזיק דפטור. hutz mereshut hamyuhedet lamazik depatur. If it's only the מזיק's
mazik domain, you're exempt.
ורשות הניזק והמזיק, Vereshut hanizak vehamazik, but if it's a shared domain,
then כשהזיק חב המזיק, keshehizik hav hamazik, then you're liable. Okay? As
long as it's not a רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, you're liable. רב
אלעזר אומר: Rav Elazar omer: פטור על השן ועל הרגל. patur al
hashen ve'al haregel. No, you're exempt if it's a shared domain. והכי
קאמר: Vehachi ka'amar: חוץ מרשות המיוחדת למזיק ורשות הניזק והמזיק נמי פטור.
hutz mereshut hamyuhedet lamazik vereshut hanizak vehamazik nami patur.
You're exempt if it's in only your domain and you're even exempt
if it's in a shared domain. The only time you're going to
be חייב hayyav is when it does damage בשדה אחר bisdeh acher
only in the other person's domain. Okay, וכשהזיק חב המזיק, vicheshehizik hav
hamazik,
so what does that last line וכשהזיק חב המזיק vicheshehizik hav hamazik
coming to say? לאתויי קרן. Le'atuyei keren. So if this is part
of the חוץ, hutz, right, if this is saying in a shared
domain you're חייב, hayyav, that's making one statement. But if this is
part of the חוץ, hutz, why are you repeating that you're חייב
hayyav to pay when your animal damages? Okay, so that's what we
said way at the beginning of the פרק, perek, that that's coming
to include קרן. keren. That you know the אבות נזיקין avot nezikin
were שן ורגל shen varegel and this is coming to include קרן.
keren. This last extra thing that you have to pay when your
animal damages. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא לשמואל, Haniha liShmuel, that's
good with שמואל, Shmuel, that's what שמואל Shmuel said. That שור shor
meant שן ורגל shen varegel and that last line includes קרן. keren.
אלא לרב דאמר תנא שור וכל מילי דשור, Ella leRav de'amar tana
shor vechol milli deshor, but according to רב Rav that the שור
shor of the first משנה mishna meant שן, shen, רגל, regel, and
קרן, keren, so חב המזיק לאתויי מאי, hav hamazik le'atuyei mai, what
is this last line doing? If this is part of the חוץ,
hutz, what do you... what is this last line telling us that
I don't already know? So the גמרא Gemara says לאתויי הך דתנו
רבנן. le'atuyei hach detanu rabbanan. So now we're going to digress for
a minute to tell me what the last line is telling me
and then we're going to go back to this question about חצר
השותפין. hatzar hashutfinn. Okay, so to tell me the following thing: וכשהזיק
חב המזיק לאתויי שומר חנם והשואל נושא שכר והשוכר. vicheshehizik hav hamazik
le'atuyei shomer hinam vehashoel nosei sachar vehasocher. All these different people, people
who are paid wat... a watchperson for free or for pay or
for somebody who rents or somebody who borrows, who all have these
liabilities. כשהזיקה בהמה ברשותן, Keshehizikah behemah birshutan,
when the animal that they were watching does damage in their understanding...
you know, in their domain, תם משלם חצי נזק ומועד משלם נזק
שלם. tam meshalem hatzi nezek umu'ad meshalem nezek shalem. Okay, that if
it's a first three times you pay half, the third time you
pay full. נפרצה בלילה, Nifretzah balailah, if it broke out in the
middle of the night, so in a way in which they were
not negligent or it was an אונס, onnes, you know, something they
couldn't control. או שפרצוה ליסטים, O shepartzuha listim, or bandits broke the
fence and it
escaped, ויצאה והזיקה פטור, veyatzah vehizikah patur, they're exempt. Okay, so basically
it's saying it's coming to include the case of a שומר. shomer.
Now, what's the חידוש, hiddush, says the גמרא, Gemara, to include the
case of a שומר? shomer? You might just say that's such a
חידוש hiddush in itself. I give you my ox to watch.
Presumably the basic liability is to watch the ox from being damaged.
And the חידוש hiddush is since you're supposed to watch the ox,
you're liable if it goes and it does damage. Okay, that's basic
חידוש hiddush number one: that a שומר shomer is liable for the
damage that the ox does. But the גמרא Gemara wants to push
it further. Let's take a look.
אמר מר: Amar mar:
וכשהזיק חב המזיק לאתויי שומר חנם והשואל נושא שכר והשוכר. Vicheshehizik hav
hamazik le'atuyei shomer hinam vehashoel nosei sachar vehasocher. היכי דמי? Heichi dami?
What's the case? אילימא דאזקיה תורא דמשאיל לתורא דשואל... Ilima de'azkeyeh tura
demash'il letura deshoel... The גמרא's Gemara going to focus on the fact
that the ברייתא braita said they did damage in their domain. Presumably
doesn't mean that the... that the ox the שומר shomer was watching
went out and damaged some third party, but it damaged some of
the property of the watcher himself. Okay, so what's the case? אילימא
דאזקיה תורא דמשאיל לתורא דשואל. Ilima de'azkeyeh tura demash'il letura deshoel. My
ox that you're watching, that when you are watching it, damaged one
of your oxen. So in that case לימא ליה, leima leih, so
I can say to you, listen buddy, אי אזיק בעלמא, ei azik
be'alma, if that ox had gored a third party's ox, בעינא לשלומי...
beina leshlumei... שלומי את, shlumei at, you'd be the one paying, because
we take the general assumption that a שומר shomer is liable for
the damage done by the animals that he's watching.
השתא דאזקה לתוריה דידך, hashta d'azka l'tora didach, so now it gored
your own ox. בעינא לשלומי, beina l'shlumei, I have to be paying
you? Okay, so what's the meaning, what's the case? The גמרא Gemara
says the case is an ox the שומר shomer is watching did
damage or we'll see maybe was damaged in the שומר's shomer property.
And there so you still have to pay. So who's paying? So
פשיטא pshita if my ox that you were watching gored your own
ox, why should I have to pay? I would say you'd be
the one paying if it gored somebody else. Why should I pay
you if it gored your own ox? So אלא, ella, rather, דאזקיה
תורא דשואל לתורא דמשאיל. d'azka tora d'shoel l'tora d'mash'il. Maybe it's the
reverse. You're watching my ox, and your ox gored my ox that
you were supposed to be watching. So and it tells me that
you have to pay
me, okay? So לתורא דשואל, l'tora d'shoel, לתורא ד... דתורא
דשואל. d'tora d'shoel. לימא ליה, leima leh, אילו אזיק בעלמא בעי שלומי
את, ilu azik b'alma ba'ei shlumei at, and I could say to
you,
listen,
so if your ox had gored somebody else's, you would have to
pay. השתא דאזקה לתורא דידך. hashta d'azka l'tora didach.
Wait a minute, how are you reading this? One
minute.
Oh oh, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. So in that case, your ox
gored my ox that you were watching, okay? You're watching my ox
and your ox gored it. So the גמרא's Gemara קשיא kushya is
then why are you only paying half damages? Let's say that my
ox that you were watching got damaged by another by some other
event. What would you have to pay me? You're the שומר. shomer.
You'd have to pay me full. Not because of ארבעה אבות נזיקין,
arba'ah avos nezikin, because of a שומר. shomer. You're watching my ox
and something happens to it and it gets damaged, right? How much
are you liable to pay me? Full amount. You're a שומר, shomer,
you're liable for damages.
Even if the goring ox is a תם? tam?
Yeah, the owner would pay maybe you back half, but you'd pay
me full because you're watching my animal. You have full liability. Let's
say the animal, right, let's say let's say the animal fell into
a well. It doesn't matter. You're just liable for damages, you're watching
my animal. So what does it mean if you're watching my animal
and your ox gored it that you pay me half? You don't
pay me half, you should be paying me full as a שומר,
shomer, not as a מזיק. mazik. Okay, so לימא ליה, leima leh,
wouldn't I say to you, אילו אזיק בעלמא בעי שלומי את? ilu
azik b'alma ba'ei shlumei at?
If it had been damaged through some other event, you would have
to pay me full.
תשלומי כולה. tashlumei kula.
השתא דאזקה תורא דידך. hashta d'azka tora didach.
Wait
did I skip a line? Okay, I'm sorry, skip backwards. לימא ליה,
leima leh, אילו איתזיק מעלמא, ilu itzik m'alma, thank you. If it
had been damaged from something from some other ox, בעי שלומי כולה,
ba'ei shlumei kula, you'd have to pay me full. כולה תורא, kula
tora, pay me back the full ox because you're a שומר. shomer.
השתא דאזקה תורא דידך, hashta d'azka tora didach, now that it was
your ox that gored my ox, פלגא ניזקא הוא דמשלמת לי, palga
nizka hu d'mshallemat li, you only pay me half? So what's the
case? Either it's obvious or it's not true. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says
לעולם le'olam or either way it's not true. לעולם דאזקה תורא דמשאיל
לתורא דשואל. le'olam d'azka tora d'mash'il l'tora d'shoel. Fine. You're watching my
ox and it gored your ox. Now, in that case, so the
גמרא's Gemara saying if that's the case, then then wait, you're watching
my ox and it gored your ox. So why am I paying
you? Right? You take liability for damage that it does. Why should
I be paying you? דהכא במאי עסקינן, d'hacha b'mai askinan, what are
we talking about? שקיבל עליו שמירת גופו ולא קיבל עליו שמירת נזקו.
she'kibbel alav shmiras gufo v'lo kibbel alav shmiras nizko. That you agreed
when you took my ox, which makes sense, you know, when you
agree to watch my thing, basically it means you're going to protect
it
from being damaged. So you could imagine a case, even though we
assume without stipulating, you're also taking on the responsibility to protect it
from damaging, you could understand a case where you stipulate, I'm only
going to protect it from damage, I am not taking any liability
if it goes and does damage. Okay, and in that case, you're
not liable for damage that it does. All right, and in that
case, it goes ahead and it gores your own ox, I have
to pay you. All right, it's a little funny. It was in
your you were my ox was in your domain, but you and
you were watching it, but you stipulated, I'm not responsible for any
damage it does. So I remain responsible for damage it does, even
if it winds up damaging your own ox, I remain responsible, okay?
But there needs to be a stipulation.
It's a stipulation that you're not taking that responsibility. Exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true,
אימא סיפא,
eima seifa, נפרצה בלילה או שפרצוה ליסטים ויצאה והזיקה פטור. nifretza b'layla
o she'partzuha listim v'yatza v'hizika patur. It says that if it broke
out at night, you're exempt because it's an אונס. onnes. הא ביום
חייב. ha b'yom chayav. That suggests that if it broke out during
the day, you the שומר shomer are חייב. chayav. הא לא קיבל
עליו שמירת נזקו. ha lo kibbel alav shmiras nizko. Why are you
חייב? chayav? You said you're you're you're exempt from any obligation if
it does damage. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, all right, that's a different
case. אם קיבל עליו שמירת נזקו, im kibbel alav shmiras nizko, if
you do agree to be liable for damage it does, חייב chayav
then you are liable for damage it does. ונפרצה בלילה או שפרצוה
ליסטים, v'nifretza b'layla o she'partzuha listim, but if it occurred by an
אונס, onnes, יצאה והזיקה. yatza v'hizika. You'd be exempt. Okay, so that's
a little bit of a digression to say what this last line
is doing. This last line is coming to deal with a case
of a שומר shomer who watched, getting us into the idea that
if a שומר shomer is watching an ox, not only does he
accept obligation for damage for damage that occurs to it, but implicitly
he accepts obligation for damage that it does do, unless he explicitly
exempts himself. All right, fine. That's a little bit of a digression,
a little distracting. Let's get back to our major point. Our major
point was a debate of how to read this line and whether
in a shared domain are you חייב chayav or פטור patur for
שן ורגל, shen v'regel, whether fundamentally you're פטור patur only in רשות
הרבים, reshus harabim, so a shared domain you'd be חייב, chayav, or
you're חייב chayav only in שדה אחר sde acher and shared domain
you'd be פטור. patur. That's the debate. So let's get back to
that.
איני, inee, is that really true that you could say that you
are
whichever one we're going by, דהא ותני רב יוסף, deha u'tani Rav
Yosef, Rav Yosef teaches, חצר השותפים, chatzer hashutafim, a shared domain, והפונדק,
vehapundak, or you basically have like a type of an inn, okay,
חייב בהן על השן ועל הרגל. chayav bahen al hashen v'al haregel.
So you're חייב, chayav, it's an explicit ברייתא baraisa that a shared
domain you're חייב. chayav. It's not a רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. תיובתא
דרבי אלעזר, tiyufta d'Rabbi Elazar, that's a challenge, a contradiction to Rabbi
Elazar who said a shared domain you're פטור. patur. So the Gemara
says, אמר לך רבי אלעזר, amar lach Rabbi Elazar, Rabbi Elazar will
say to you, ותסברה, u'tispira, you think that makes sense? מתניתין מינה
פליגי, matnisa mini pligi, is there, does
a ברייתא baraisa not argue on this? You can't just challenge me
from one text. I've got a תוספתא tosefta that says the opposite,
that's just like me, that a shared domain you're actually פטור. patur.
Okay, where do I have it? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, baraisa, ארבעה כללות היה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר בנזיקין. arba
klalos haya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer benizikin. Four general rules, meaning
four types of domains. כל שהוא רשות לניזק ולא למזיק, kol shehu
reshus lenizak v'lo lemazik, if it is only the damagee's רשות, reshus,
okay, חייב בכל, chayav bakol, you're חייב chayav in everything, קרן keren
and שן shen and רגל. regel. That's שדה אחר. sde acher. That
you incur, you did this incursion into somebody else's domain.
למזיק ולא לניזק, lemazik v'lo lenizak, it's only the damager's domain, פטור,
patur, you're exempt. That's תורך ברשותי מאי בעי, torcha b'reshus'i mai ba'ee,
what right do you have to come into my domain? Okay, those
are the two easy cases. פטור מכל, patur mikol, you're fully exempt.
Now, לזה ולזה, laze u'laze, if it is a shared domain, כגון
חצר השותפים והבקעה, kegon chatzer hashutafim vehabika, like a something owned jointly
owned or a valley, פטור בהן על השן ועל הרגל. patur bahen
al hashen v'al haregel. You're exempt for שן shen and רגל. regel.
So there you have exactly the opposite of the previous ברייתא. baraisa.
One ברייתא baraisa says a shared domain you're חייב chayav in שן
shen and רגל. regel. This ברייתא baraisa says a shared domain you're
פטור patur in שן shen and רגל. regel. And then it says,
however by קרן, keren, when it comes to קרן, keren, על הנגיחה
ועל הנגיפה ועל הנשיכה ועל הרביצה ועל הבעיטה, al hanegicha v'al hanegifa
v'al haneshicha v'al harevitza v'al habe'ita, all these other acts which are
forms of קרן, keren, kicking and crouching and whatever, תם משלם חצי
נזק ומועד משלם נזק שלם. tam meshalem chatzi nezek u'muad meshalem nezek
shalem. There you pay half or full based on תם tam or
מועד. muad. But anyway, the עיקר ikkar for us is a shared
domain it says you're פטור patur as opposed to the previous ברייתא
baraisa that said a shared domain you're חייב. chayav. Now, the fourth
domain, what's the fourth? לא לזה ולא לזה, lo laze v'lo laze,
neither of us have rights to it. So that sounds like it's
a third party's domain, right? My ox goes into Shimon's yard and
gores Reuven's ox. Okay, so neither of us have rights to be
there. That's sort of what it sounds like. The Gemara's going to
redefine it, but that's sort of what it sounds like, that it's
a third party's domain, כגון חצר שאינה של שניהם, kegon chatzer she'eino
she'lo shenehem, חייב בו על השן ועל הרגל, chayav bo al hashen
v'al haregel, you're חייב chayav on שן shen and רגל regel because
it would be a שדה אחר. sde acher. It would still be
a domain I have no rights to. So it went into Reuven's
domain and it ate Shimon's fruit, but nevertheless, my ox had no
right there. It's still a שדה אחר. sde acher.
על הנגיחה ועל הנשיכה ועל הרביצה ועל הנגיפה ועל הרביצה ועל הבעיטה,
al hanegicha v'al haneshicha v'al harevitza v'al hanegifa v'al harevitza v'al habe'ita,
תם משלם חצי נזק ומועד משלם נזק שלם. tam meshalem chatzi nezek
u'muad meshalem nezek shalem. Okay, so anyway, so it sounds like we're
going to get back to that last one, but that last one
sounds like if it's a third party's domain, from my perspective, that's
just as much as a שדה אחר sde acher and I wind
up paying for שן shen and רגל. regel. But however we explain
that last case, קתני מיהא, katani mihu, we taught nevertheless the middle
the third case, that in a case of חצר השותפים והבקעה, chatzer
hashutafim vehabika, if it's a partner-owned
field or it's a valley, פטור בהן על השן ועל הרגל, patur
bahen al hashen v'al haregel, you're exempt in שן shen and רגל.
regel. So look, it seems like it's clearly a מחלוקת machlokes of
ברייתות. beraisos. This מחלוקת אמוראים machlokes amoraim seems like a debate of
the תנאים. tannaim. Is a shared domain חייב chayav or פטור patur
on שן ורגל? shen v'regel. Yes?
Did you say anything about what's the thing with a בקעה? bika?
I never understood that. Like what's the deal with a valley?
Why is a valley it's considered to be both of ours? Yeah,
so it seems to be I was holding that off a second
because the Gemara's going to focus on it, but I'll answer you
now. It seems to be the idea that a valley, it's not
technically that I have rights to the valley, a valley might be
like ownerless, but it's similar in the sense that everybody, anybody can
use a valley, right? You have a right to be there, okay,
if it's like a ownerless valley, and on the other hand... it's
not like a רשות הרבים. Reshus HaRabim. A רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim
everybody has rights, but it is a high traffic type of an
area. A valley, like we both have a right to it's like
a חצר של שנים. Chatzer Shel Shnayim. We both have a right
to be there, but we don't necessarily have to expect that there's
going to be like a lot of other traffic there either. So
I think that's what the גמרא's Gemara getting at with the valley,
okay, but let's take a look. Okay.
So it says like this, קשיא אהדדי, Kashya Adadi, so this is
a contradiction. So כי תניא ההיא, Ki Tanya Hi, ah, so rather
than saying that it's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, we're going to
have a way to reconcile the
תנאים. Tannaim. כי תניא ההיא בחצר המיוחדת לזה ולזה בין לפירות בין
לשוורים. Ki Tanya Hi Bechatzer Meyuchedes Laze Uleze Bein Lapeiros Bein Lishvarim.
ההיא דרב יוסף בחצר המיוחדת לפירות ואינה מיוחדת לשוורים. Hahi Dir Yosef
Bechatzer Meyuchedes Lapeiros Ve'eina Meyuchedes Lishvarim. So now we're going to raise
the degree of complexity and we're going to say: what does it
mean you have a right to be there? Do you have a
right for your ox to be there, or do you have a
right for your fruit to be there? Because my ox ate your
fruit. So up until now we've been assuming we both have a
right to do either thing there. Okay, but now the גמרא's Gemara
going to distinguish. So let's imagine that in the first case, we
both had a right for oxen and we had a right for
fruit. So what do you think that would make it? Would that
make it like a רשות... Reshus that should make it like a,
right, רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim because everybody has a right to do
everything there. And that could be a case that you should be
exempt, you should be פטור. Patur. Okay, because you all have a
right, right? So basically what I so let's contrast the two. ההיא
דרב יוסף, Hahi Dir Yosef, the case where רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said you'd be חייב, Chayav, בחצר המיוחדת לפירות ואינה מיוחדת לשוורים. Bechatzer
Meyuchedes Lapeiros Ve'eina Meyuchedes Lishvarim. That makes a lot of sense. I
have a right to leave my fruit here, you don't have a
right to have your ox here. So in that case, it's really
like a שדה אחר, S'dei Acher, right? Because your ox had no
right to be here. Yeah, you with me here? Okay, so your
ox had no right to be here.
So it's some kind of
משותף Mshutaf לגבי legabei פירות Peiros
only, but not to bring our animals. Exactly.
לגבי שן הוי חצר הניזק.
Legabei
Shein Havei Chatzer Hanizak.
דיקא נמי דקתני הכא דומיא דפונדק וקתני התם דומיא
דביקא. Dika Nami Diktani Hacha Dumya DePundak Vekatani Hasam Dumya Devika. The
one that said חייב, Chayav, the ברייתא Baraisa spoke about it like
an inn. You don't bring your ox into an inn. You have
a right to have your property in your inn, to bring your
bags, but you don't have a right to bring your ox into
the inn. And there it says like a valley. A valley you
have your right for your ox and for your fruit. שמע מינה.
Shma Mina. Okay, so basically what we've done is we've said that
when you have it's not exactly clear if the ברייתא Baraisa if
the גמרא Gemara now is resolving a middle case. Because when it
says you have רשות Reshus, for שוורים Shvarim and פירות, Peiros, it
says that's going to be like a רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim and
you're going to be exempt. Okay, if it's going to say if
you have you have רשות, Reshus אין
לו רשות
לשוורים,
Ein Lo
Reshus Lishvarim, so obviously it's a שדה אחר. S'dei Acher. Your ox
isn't supposed to be here. Right? If you don't have רשות Reshus
for שוורים, Shvarim, that's an easy case. It's a שדה אחר. S'dei
Acher. When you have רשות Reshus for both, is that saying that's
like a רשות הרבים reshus harabim. because you have רשות for both?
Or is it basically saying no, fundamentally חצר השותפים, Chatzer Hashutafim, you're
exempt. The only case you're חייב Chayav is if your ox didn't
have a right to be there. So you know, where is the
גמרא Gemara basically drawing the line? I would argue the גמרא's Gemara
basically drawing the line here: it has to be שדה אחר, S'dei
Acher, and the only time it's שדה אחר S'dei Acher is if
you don't have a right for bringing your ox. So when did
it say that if you have if it's a חצר השותפים Chatzer
Hashutafim you're going to be חייב, Chayav, it didn't really mean חצר
השותפים. Chatzer Hashutafim. It really meant fine, you can have your fruit
there, but you're not allowed to have your ox there.
Fundamentally, it has to be שדה אחר S'dei Acher and you're only
going to be חייב Chayav if you have no right for your
ox. If you have a right for your ox, you're going to
be פטור. Patur. Okay? Now, the case that the גמרא Gemara did
not deal with, which is a מחלוקת רש"י תוספות, Machlokes Rashi Tosfos,
is what if you have a right for your ox and you
don't have a right for your fruit? Okay, so that's a מחלוקת
רש"י תוספות. Machlokes Rashi Tosfos. All right, we'll get to that. But
anyway, but the גמרא Gemara seems to be doing, and it even
quoted the פסוק Pasuk of שדה אחר, S'dei Acher, was it seems
to be saying conceptually anything that's not שדה אחר S'dei Acher you're
going to be פטור. Patur. You're only חייב Chayav when your ox
did not have a right to be there, when it's אינה מיוחדת
לשוורים. Eina Meyuchedes Lishvarim.
Yeah, and I'm thinking about this in terms to me it sounds
like you have a חצר השותפים Chatzer Hashutafim and there's like bylaws.
Right? There's an agreement, like we can keep these things here but
not those. Yeah, exactly.
That's basically what it is. And that by the way explains why
בקעה Bika is put in the פטור Patur category, because even if
I don't have rights to a בקעה, Bika, like I don't have
an ownership over it, but my ox is allowed to be there.
The basic rule is wherever my ox is allowed to be I'm
exempt. The only time I'm חייב Chayav is in spaces that I'm
not allowed to bring my ox into. Okay, and it's really a
conceptual שדה אחר S'dei Acher definition. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this, מתקיף לה רב זביד. Maskif Lah Rav Zevid. One minute. כיון
דמיוחדת לפירות הא בעינן וביער בשדה אחר וליכא. keivan d'meyuchedet l'peirot, ha
ba'ina ubi'ur bisdeh acher v'leika. He didn't buy this. If I'm allowed
to keep my fruit there, it's not a fully שדה אחר. sdeh
acher. Maybe my ox can't be there, but it's also my domain,
I have a right to keep my fruit there.
אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye no, כיון דאינה מיוחדת לשוורים שדה
אחר קרינן ביה. keivan d'eini meyuchedet l'shvarim sdeh acher karinan beih. No,
no, no. Since you don't have a right for your ox, from
your ox's perspective, it's a שדה אחר. sdeh acher. It's very nice
you can keep your fruit there, but your ox had no right
to be there. From your ox's perspective, it was a domain he
could not go into. אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא לימא מדמתניתין
לא פליגי אמוראי נמי לא פליגי. Amar lei Rav Acha miDifti l'Ravina,
leima mid'masnisa lo pligi Amora'ei nami lo pligi. Ah, now we've reconciled
the ברייתות. braitas. We said they don't disagree. Okay, basically,
if you have a right for your ox, you're פטור. patur. If
you don't have a right for an ox, you're חייב. chayav. And
we reconciled it. So, if that's true, maybe the אמוראים Amora'im weren't
disagreeing, they were just talking about different scenarios. One was a scenario
that you had a right for your ox, and one was a
scenario you didn't have a right for your ox. אמר ליה אין,
Amar lei in, yeah, why not? Let's say everybody agrees. שלום על
ישראל. Shalom al Yisrael. ואם תמצא לומר פליגי, Ve'im timtzo lomar pligi,
or say they do disagree,
בקושיא דרבי זירא ופרוקא דאביי פליגי. b'kushya d'Rabbi Zeira uparuka d'Abaye pligi.
What they disagree with is interesting. The גמרא Gemara says they don't
disagree with when you have rights for both. When you have a
right for both, when you have a right for your ox, everybody
agrees you're פטור. patur. If your ox had a right to be
there, everybody agrees you're פטור. patur. The only debate they're having is
this case. When your ox doesn't have a right and your fruit
does have a right to be there. One position says it's שדה
אחר sdeh acher because your ox shouldn't be there, and the other
says you can't call it שדה אחר sdeh acher as long as
I have some right. As long as I have a right to
have my fruit here, even though I don't have a right for
my ox, you can't call it שדה אחר. sdeh acher. So they're
debating, which is shocking. You would think it would be obvious if
my ox doesn't have a right, it's שדה אחר. sdeh acher. No,
maybe they're debating that, and one's saying as long as you have
some right, it's not שדה אחר. sdeh acher. So what the גמרא's
Gemara completely doing, and this is important conceptually, is it to say
it doesn't have to be like רשות הרבים. reshus harabim The
conceptually it's not that רשות הרבים reshus harabim you're exempt, that's not
what the פסוק pasuk says. The פסוק pasuk says שדה אחר sdeh
acher you're חייב. chayav. You're only חייב chayav if you can define
it as שדה אחר. sdeh acher. So anytime my ox has a
right to be there, it is not שדה אחר. sdeh acher. The
only thing that would be שדה אחר sdeh acher is my ox
has no right to be there. And even there, it could be
that if I have a right to keep my fruit there, it's
not enough of a שדה אחר. sdeh acher. But once my ox
has a right, it's no longer שדה אחר sdeh acher and I'm
going to be פטור. patur. Alright, so everybody see that point? It's
not that you need to be רשות הרבים to be פטור, patur,
you need to be שדה אחר sdeh acher to be חייב. chayav.
And only if your ox has no right can we begin to
say it's not שדה אחר. sdeh acher.
We're drawing a distinction between a shared orchard, as it were, and
a shared pasture. Okay. And we're talking about a situation where an
ox damages other ox?
No, no, no, it's שן ורגל, shen v'regel he's eating the fruit.
He's eating the fruit.
Right.
None of this is קרן. keren.
It's all שן ורגל. shen v'regel. שן ורגל shen va-regel you're always
חייב. chayav.
שן ורגל. shein va'regel, Right.
Okay?
That's why it's a
שדה אחר sdeh acher emphasis. Like I can bring my fruit into
your house and by the way, I brought my pitbull here also.
Because I can bring my fruit in there, it's not...
No, I think if I give you permission to bring your fruit,
I would still be... even the opinion that says when I have
an ownership that allows me to bring my fruit, it's not שדה
אחר. sdeh acher. If it's your thing and you give me permission
to bring your fruit, I think it still is שדה אחר. sdeh
acher. Yeah.
So what happens if you share an orchard? Right. And I stipulate,
oh by the way, I'm going to let my ox graze there
also.
You don't need a... well, anything we stipulate to, we stipulate to.
I mean that's between us.
That's why I'm
saying that's where the stipulation was. Right, right, right. But if we
share an orchard... I mean that's the funny thing, we share an
orchard and it's very clear we're keeping our animal... the question is
the opposite. We share an orchard but it's very clear we're keeping
our animals out of here. We have a fence around this orchard.
Those animals are a hazard, they're going to rip up the crops.
And nevertheless, your animal walks in and eats. You say, hey, at
the end of the day it was my orchard too. It's not
שדה אחר. sdeh acher. Okay, that's weird. So the גמרא Gemara is
saying that's the only case where they maybe are debating. But the
bottom line is anytime my ox has a right, there's no question
you're exempt. So it really shows that we're defining שדה אחר sdeh
acher and we're trying to really define it, you know, and that
is a narrow definition. At the end of the day, it makes
sense that if my ox doesn't have a right, even though it's
partly my orchard, I... my ox shouldn't be there, I'm going to
be חייב. chayav. Okay, let's get back now and unpack the ברייתא.
braita. גופא. Gufa. ארבעה כללות היה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר בנזיקין.
Arba klalos haya Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer binzikin. כל שרשות לניזק ולא למזיק
חייב בכל. Kol she'reshus l'nizak v'lo l'mazik chayav bakol. So if it
is a... goes into your domain, I'm חייב chayav for everything, בכל.
bakol. Okay, you know, even if it's a case of... whatever, you
know, that's שורך ברשותי מאי בעי, shorchecha birshusi ma ba'ei, like you
know, I'm always חייב chayav when... And it goes into—no, I'm sorry,
that's not שור ברשותי. shor bireshuti. That's going into שטח אחר. shtach
acheir. It goes into your domain, I'm חייב chayav in everything. על
הכל לא קתני; al hakol lo katani; it doesn't say for all
damages, אלא חייב בכל. ela chayav bakol. You're חייב chayav fully, בכולי
נזק. bekuli nezek. So that sounds like when my ox goes into
your domain, it's שטח אחר shtach acheir and damages, I pay full
damages, even in a case of קרן. keren. Okay, now we saw
this possibility before, that if it goes into a space it has
no right to be, then even קרן keren pays full. מאני? mani?
Now that's a debate of תנאי. tannai. Who is that? רבי טרפון
היא. Rabbi Tarfon hi. רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. דאמר משונה קרן בחצר
הניזק נזק שלם משלם. de-amar meshuneh keren be-chatzer hanizak nezek shalem meshalem.
When something is unusual, משונה, meshuneh, which is a type of a
קרן, keren, we'll get to that idea later, how משונה meshuneh when
it does something weird, it's considered קרן. keren. Anyway, בחצר הניזק, be-chatzer
hanizak, when it is in the ניזק'ס nizak's domain, נזק שלם משלם,
nezek shalem meshalem, you pay full, no longer you pay half. If
it's actually in a space it's not allowed to be, or it's
in the ניזק'ס nizak's domain, full payment. אימא סיפא. eima seifa. Okay,
maybe that is what the ברייתא braita is going like. Let's look
at the end of the ברייתא. braita. לא לזה ולא לזה, lo
lazeh velo lazeh, if it has—if it is neither person's domain,
כגון חצר שאינה של שניהם, kegon chatzer she-eina shel sheneihem, חייב על
השן ועל הרגל. chayav al hashen ve-al haregel. Now, I would assume
that meant it's a third party's domain, right? What does it mean
לא לזה ולא לזה? lo lazeh velo lazeh? Some third party? מאי
לא לזה ולא לזה? mai lo lazeh velo lazeh? אילימא לא לזה
ולא לזה כלל אלא דאחר? ilima lo lazeh velo lazeh klal ela
de-acher? It's some third party's domain. So my ox goes into ראובן'ס
Reuven's domain and eats שמעון'ס Shimon's fruit. והא בעינא ובער בשדה אחר
וליכא. ve-ha be'ina u-vi'er bi-sdei acheir ve-leika. Notice how the גמרא Gemara
is completely focused on שדה אחר sdei acheir and defining it very
narrowly. I would think that if my ox goes into ראובן'ס Reuven's
domain and it has no right to go into ראובן'ס Reuven's yard,
even if it winds up eating שמעון'ס Shimon's fruit, my ox shouldn't
have been there and I pay. But the גמרא Gemara says no,
because it says ובער בשדה אחר, u-vi'er bi-sdei acheir, presumably the גמרא
Gemara says that that means is that it's only liable if it
goes into שמעון'ס Shimon's domain and eats שמעון'ס Shimon's fruit, right? Because
I don't get exactly why the גמרא Gemara assumes that. Once we
said that שדה אחר sdei acheir means a domain that my ox
is not allowed to go into, okay, but it is basically saying
that it has to basically that it's only חייב chayav if it
consumes something that is the other person's שדה. sadeh. It goes into
a field that is somebody else's and it consumes of that person's
field, or it consumes property in that person's field. And this is
somebody else's property it consumed. So again, it's strange but the גמרא
Gemara assumes that based on what we just said, I would think,
hey, if my ox doesn't have a right there, it's שדה אחר.
sdei acheir. No, it has to be you're consuming the food or
the property of the domain that you are in. Yes.
So what if שמעון—what Shimon if ראובן Reuven gave שמעון Shimon permission
to put שמעון'ס Shimon's fruit in
ראובן'ס—right, Reuven's so then that might be it might become it sort
of might be like a type of a שמעון'ס Shimon's domain in
that case. That might be שמעון'ס Shimon's domain. I mean if ראובן
Reuven let שמעון Shimon keep his fruit there then it might be
a type of שמעון'ס Shimon's domain as well and it might be
a שדה אחר. sdei acheir. But if שמעון Shimon doesn't have right,
the גמרא'ס Gemara's spelling that out. The funny thing is the גמרא
Gemara just takes it for granted. I have no right to be
there but it's not שדה אחר sdei acheir because it was somebody
else's property that was being consumed, right? So that's funny that the
גמרא Gemara just takes that for granted. All right. So and it
rejects what is a completely reasonable read of the ברייתא. braita. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does say. אלא פשיטא לא לזה
ולא לזה אלא דחד. ela peshita lo lazeh velo lazeh ela de-chad.
It means it's not both of theirs' domain, it's only one of
theirs' domain. Okay, very funny. It's not ראובן'ס Reuven's and it's not
both—it's not ראובן Reuven and שמעון'ס Shimon's domain, it's only ראובן'ס Reuven's
domain. Sort of like the joke which is, I'm holding two coins
in my hands and they total thirty-five cents and one of them
isn't a quarter, what are they? The answer is a quarter and
a dime. The other one is the quarter. So it's not this
one, it's לא לזה ולא לזה, lo lazeh velo lazeh, it's not
this or that, it's only one of theirs. Okay anyway, וקתני סיפא.
u-katani seifa. All
right, so anyway, read that last line that you're חייב נזק שלם
chayav nezek shalem when it's basically it's reading it again as a
case of רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. Okay, which is what we said
earlier was רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. וקתני סיפא תם משלם חצי נזק
ומועד משלם נזק שלם. u-katani seifa tam meshalem chatzi nezek u-muad meshalem
nezek shalem. אתאן לרבנן דאמרי משונה קרן בחצר הניזק חצי נזק הוא
דמשלם. atan le-rabbanan de-amri meshuneh keren be-chatzer hanizak chatzi nezek hu de-meshalem.
So now that's saying like basically what did the ברייתא braita say?
The ברייתא braita said if it is—if it's the רשות מזיק, reshut
mazik, okay, it said you're פטור. patur. רשות ניזק, reshut nizak, it
said you're חייב chayav and the גמרא Gemara read בכל, bakol, חייב
בכל chayav bakol means that even קרן keren pays full. Okay, רשות
שניהם, reshut sheneihem, okay, that's where it said you're פטור patur on
שן ורגל shein va'regel? because that's what we've been saying, right, רשות
שניהם reshut sheneihem basically is פטור. patur. And then it said לא
לזה ולא לזה, lo lazeh velo lazeh, which we assumed meant a
third party's, but for some reason the גמרא Gemara rejected it, okay,
that said קרן... keren... half for קרן keren like normal. But the
גמרא Gemara rejects it. I'm sorry, a third party does not constitute
שדה אחר, sdeh acher, so לא לזה ולא לזה lo lazeh velo
lazeh means it's not both of theirs, but it's only one of
theirs, and it backs meaning ניזק. nizak. So now that we've got
this back to meaning ניזק, nizak, and that's why you pay full
for שן ורגל, shen v'regel. it says why you only paying half
for קרן? keren? Here we said חייב בכל, chayav bakol, that you
pay full for קרן. keren. Okay, so what or you could actually
say why are we repeating it? It's not four, it's three, right?
And you know, we take something that means the fourth thing and
we and we say that it means something we said earlier. But
in רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, קרן keren pays שלם shaleim even if
it's תם? tam? Yeah, well according to רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, that's
what we said בכל bakol meant. Okay, it's a debate of תנאים,
tannaim, but now if we're going to read this as ניזק nizak
again and say half, that's the רבנן rabbanan that argue on רבי
טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. So which is it? Does נזק nezek pay full
or does נזק nezek pay... or does קרן keren pay
full or does קרן keren pay half? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says: אלא פשיטא לא לזה ולא לזה אלא דחד. ela peshita lo
lazeh velo lazeh ela dechad.
It's not this and this, it's one of theirs, meaning it's ניזק.
nizak. דתני סיפא תם משלם חצי נזק ומועד משלם שלם. detani seifa
tam meshalem chatzi nezek umuad meshalem shaleim. אתו רבנן, atu rabbanan, that's
going like the rabbis, דאמרי משונה בקרן חצי נזק משלם, deamri meshuneh
bekeren chatzi nezek meshalem, that קרן keren only pays half damages in
חצר הניזק. chatzar hanizak. רישא רבי טרפון וסיפא רבנן. reisha Rabbi Tarfon
useifa rabbanan. Can the beginning be רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and the
end be רבנן? rabbanan? אין, in, yes. דאמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה,
deamar lei Shmuel leRav Yehuda, שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, שיננא, shinena, sharp one, שבוק מתניתין, shevok matnitin, forget about the
משנה Mishnah that you're finding it difficult to read the משנה Mishnah
going according to different opinions. ותא בתראי, veta batrai, just follow me,
listen to me. רישא רבי טרפון וסיפא רבנן. reisha Rabbi Tarfon useifa
rabbanan. Okay, so it's a completely bizarre. We have something which clearly
means a third party's domain, we reinterpret it to mean a ניזק's
nizak domain, and then the ברייתא Braita has different rulings about the
ניזק's nizak domain. So we say this is רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
and this is רבנן. rabbanan. Okay. רבינא משמיה דרב אמר כולי רבי
טרפון היא, Ravina mishmei deRav amar kulei Rabbi Tarfon hi, it's all
רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. ומה לא לזה ולא לזה? umai lo lazeh
velo lazeh? What does it mean לא לזה ולא לזה? lo lazeh
velo lazeh? Now here's where we get to the case we didn't
deal with before. לא לזה ולא לזה לפירות אלא דחד. lo lazeh
velo lazeh lepeirot ela dechad. לזה ולזה לשוורים. lazeh velazeh leshvarim. It's
a case where both oxen have a right to be there, but
only one of us has a right to have the fruits there.
לגבי שן הוי חצר הניזק. legabei shein havei chatzar hanizak. לגבי קרן
הוי רשות הרבים. legabei keren havei reshut harabbim. Okay, so basically here's
the story. We both have a right to be there, but only
you have a right to have your fruit there. Okay, so my
ox goes in, we both have a right to have our oxen
there, but only you have a right to have your fruit there,
I don't have a right to have my fruit here. So the
way רש"י Rashi is... רש"י, Rashi, this is רש"י's Rashi גרסא girsa
of the גמרא. Gemara. This is the case we didn't deal with,
right? We dealt with a case where nobody has a right to
bring their ox, right? Or they both have a right to bring
their ox and their fruit. Let's say they both have a right
to bring their ox, but only one of them has to bring
their fruit. According to רש"י, Rashi, that's enough to make it considered
שדה אחר sdeh acher and רשות הניזק. reshut hanizak. Now that's a
little bit bizarre, right? Because if I have a right to have
my ox there, why is it considered שדה אחר? sdeh acher? Okay,
I can't put my fruit there, you can put your fruit, but
I have a right to have my ox, why is it שדה
אחר? sdeh acher? Okay, so רש"י Rashi says that this שדה אחר,
sdeh acher, it's either I don't have a right to have my
ox there or I don't have a right to have my fruit
there. Either one makes it to some degree not fully my my
domain. If there's an element of אחר acher involved, רש"י Rashi says
that that would make it not fully mine. But תוספות Tosafot disagrees.
He says how could you have a right to have your ox
and it be considered שדה אחר? sdeh acher? Okay, so if you
look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says like this: רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam גרס garis לא לזה ולא לזה לפירות אלא דחד. lo lazeh
velo lazeh lepeirot ela dechad. Or it says גרס garis לא לזה
ולא לזה לשוורים. lo lazeh velo lazeh leshvarim. לגבי שן הוי חצר
הניזק. legabei shein havei chatzar hanizak. לגבי שוורים הוי קרן ברשות הרבים,
legabei shvarim havei keren birshut harabbim, כיון דהוי רשותו. keivan dehavei reshuto.
So it gets very complicated. But anyway, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam goes
back to reading it like we read before, that you don't have
your right to bring your ox in there. All right, so anyway,
we have now one minute left and I have to try to
wrap this point up, though it's become the most complicated thing. Let's
just finish this. Okay, so let's blow it up. Let's do this
one more time. רבינא משמיה דרב אמר כולי רבי טרפון היא, Ravina
mishmei deRav amar kulei Rabbi Tarfon hi, it's רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon.
So when it's real רשות הניזק, reshut hanizak, you're חייב בכל. chayav
bakol. Here, why are you going to be paying only half קרן
keren and full שן ורגל? shen v'regel. Because it's not totally רשות
הניזק. reshut hanizak. I'll read it רש"י's Rashi way. ומה לא לזה
ולא לזה? umai lo lazeh velo lazeh? לא לזה ולא לזה לפירות
אלא דחד. lo lazeh velo lazeh lepeirot ela dechad. לזה ולזה לשוורים.
lazeh velazeh leshvarim. Because you're both allowed to bring your ox in
there, you're going to pay half for קרן. keren. You can't tell
me my ox had no right to be here, my ox did
have a right to be here. So I'm only going to pay
the classic half for קרן. keren. But because only one of us
had a right to have our fruit there, it is enough of
a שדה אחר sdeh acher that I... I'm going to pay for
שן shen ורגל. v'regel, Okay, דלגבי שן הוי ליה חצר הניזק, del'gabi
shen havei lei chatzer hanizak, לגבי קרן הוי ליה רשות הרבים. legabi
keren havei lei reshus harabbim. People sort of get it? Now, yes,
sort of? No? Since you and I are both can have our
oxen in there. You can have your fruit, you can't have your
fruit. Right. So if my ox eats your fruit, I'm פטור. patur.
If your ox eats mine, you have to pay. Right. Right. Okay,
so because my ox is allowed to be there, I only pay
half for קרן. keren. Because you're allowed to have fruit and I'm
not, it's enough of a שדה אחר sadeh acher that I'm going
to pay full if it eats your fruit. Right. Okay, but the
irony being, I'm allowed to have my ox there and it's still
considered שדה אחר sadeh acher for שן shen ורגל. v'regel? And תוספות
Tosfos has a different read. Let's just turn the page and finish
this up. אי הכי ארבעה שלשה הוי? ee hachi arba'ah sheloshah havei?
Is that really four categories? It's really three conceptual categories applied to
four different cases. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak, fine. שלשה כללות בארבעה מקומות. sheloshah klalos b'arba'ah mekomos. Fine. Three
conceptual categories apply to four different scenarios. But at the end of
the day, right, it becomes very interesting because רש"י Rashi says exactly
opposite I think what we would have expected, that if I can
have a case where my ox can have a right to be
there and it's still considered שדה אחר. sadeh acher. Okay, תוספות Tosfos
rejects that. תוספות, Tosfos, to be a שדה אחר, sadeh acher, it
has to be
that I did not have a right to
have my ox there at all. All right. All right, we will
finally pick up with the new משנה mishna tomorrow.